Suraj Racha: Namaste, everyone. A warm welcome to our second session of IKS Training.
Suraj Racha: So, we'll be beginning in a short while.
Suraj Racha: And before that…
Suraj Racha: I'll just complete a small presentation, which was pending yesterday, which might be useful for a lot of us.
Suraj Racha: So… There are a few more things.
Suraj Racha: Which we are offering, and which may be of interest for all of us.
Suraj Racha: First of all, again, a warm greeting to our IKS counselor training program.
Suraj Racha: And…
Suraj Racha: Again, again, welcome, Goin Provoji and Karan Mithilji. Goen Provoji is having more than 3 decades of experience in counseling. He has been leading, spearheading a lot of curriculs and alternate educational institutes across Baharat.
Suraj Racha: He's the author of many, many renowned books, scholar in a lot of scriptures.
Suraj Racha: And an expert in IKE's psychology, and Dr. Karan Mittel is having more than 6 years of experience of integral psychology, combining his expertise from MDBAs, counseling, Naishastar philosophy, and Jodhis.
Suraj Racha: Now, what we're getting here…
Suraj Racha: all of the participants will also be getting our Vidhur app, a 6-month complimentary subscription, which I'll be going through. And our app, as you can see.
Suraj Racha: actually has a lot of IKS tools, a trained chatbot, journaling, data-driven parameter tracking, assessments, task planner, library, and organization and counselor support.
Suraj Racha: What might be of more interest here is we are… because many of us are actually counselors, some of us may be spiritual mentors, some of us may be psychologists or life coaches, or some of us may be teachers. So, there's a very interesting tool that we are offering at a very, very discounted,
Suraj Racha: price is you can onboard all your organization. Basically, if you're having 100 mentees with you, you can onboard your mentees on our Vidur platform. All of us, all of your mentees will be using the application, will be giving the reports, and the reports will be available to you, the data will be available to you. So this
Suraj Racha: helps you build your own community, it helps you track what is happening with your mentees, and also it helps you make a constant connection. So, your own profession stays intact, but we, as a platform, provide you with the required ICASE tools. With that, I'll also…
Suraj Racha: Like, to have a very, very brief run-through of our application, so that we get a feel of, what the app looks like.
Suraj Racha: Okay.
Suraj Racha: So, here's our weather app.
Suraj Racha: As you can see.
Suraj Racha: There's a lot of, plenty of, parameters which we track, starting from mood score, energy level, hydration, stress, etc.
Suraj Racha: Which are based on the case, the tracking methodologies based on Indian Knowledge System. Then there's a journaling, which all of your mentees, as well as you can do. We have built our own chatbot.
Suraj Racha: We have built our own chatbot, which is trained upon Indian psychology, Ayurveda, Dhinacharya, and Panchakosh. So, this is a very authentic, ICAS-based chatbot, which can be used as constant support.
Suraj Racha: Then, we are having our own library, which is a replacement to a lot of other content bombardment which an individual goes through. You can directly access the courses and content through this.
Suraj Racha: More importantly.
Suraj Racha: more importantly, we have curated a lot of assessments. For example, Chitta Bhumi hails from the Yoga Shastras, then there's Kafabitavata, there is nakshatra-based assessment, Satvarajasthamas-based assessments, and your mentees, or you yourself, can take these assessments
Suraj Racha: You can… Get your reports. I'll be showing just one report here.
Suraj Racha: You can…
Suraj Racha: Get your detailed report, or your mentee's detailed report, and this helps bring you… build your organization, it helps understand your own mentee better. So these tools are provided by Vidur.
Suraj Racha: At the same time, if you are a counselor, you can actually put your counselor notes. For example, you are a counselor 200 different people, so all of them can access your own counseling notes.
Suraj Racha: So, all of this is provided by our Vidur application. The same is also available on the website. For some reason, if someone is not able to use the app, all the same features are available on the website.
Suraj Racha: So… With this.
Suraj Racha: We'll begin with the session, but this was an addition which, which I like to add on. And if anyone is… so, definitely, all of us are getting the 6-month subscription for free, which we are,
Suraj Racha: Which you please use and tell back your feedback. At the same time, if anyone is interested in availing the organizational features of Vidur, you can reach out to us.
Suraj Racha: Thank you, and with that, I would like to invite Goon Prabhi and Baran Mitel to take the session forward.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, namaste, everyone. I welcome you to the day, too.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And yesterday we saw, basically, you know, how the definition of mind basically lacks, or it's not probably a cumulative definition in various models of Western psychology. And now one particular model kind of governs the further diagnosis and treatment, but it's like a part of the whole, but not the whole.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So we try to dwell on that, and also we try to dwell on our understanding of mind, our beliefs about mind, how have these beliefs impacted us? So we try to see all those,
Dr. Karan Mittal: features about mind, or just the mana, if I put it in the Indian term, yesterday. And today, we'll probably take a step further into our training, and we'll also talk about beliefs, and we'll also talk about the current Jaguishtaya, and other things that our rishis have kind of corresponded.
Dr. Karan Mittal: for understanding the Indian psychology. So basically, these are the…
Dr. Karan Mittal: These are the three points that we'll be covering today. Of course, today also, we'll have more deeper exercises, for our own self-work, as well as, you know, starting to kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: how to kind of interact with the client, or interact with your counseling. Some more exercises, some more bare work will happen today. But yesterday, when I was kind of, you know, hopping into different breakout rooms, I just noticed a few things, and before we started today, I would like to just
Dr. Karan Mittal: kind of,
Dr. Karan Mittal: clarify on certain requirements of the breakout room. The first being, the goal when you are in a breakout room is to provide that safety container to the person who's speaking.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So we don't get into a judgmental question, or asking too many questions. Sometimes as spiritual counselors, or sometimes as even psychologists, what happens is we try to be on that pedestal and look at the client in an inferior way.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so one of the self-works that happens is we try to be, we try to come at the same level of the client. We say that we… we try to meet the client where he is, or he or she is, and not… not impose our, our understanding, etc. Second thing is confidentiality, probably.
Dr. Karan Mittal: you… unless you have an explicit consent from the person who's speaking, you don't share it in a bigger group, like when we come back and we discuss, so that's confidentiality. And also, the containers or the breakout rooms are designed for more of self-work in this
Dr. Karan Mittal: first 2 or 3 days, and then a bit more of counseling work. So, the most important part over… in those 15 minutes is see how deeper you can go in your own reflections, rather than
Dr. Karan Mittal: pushing someone to go deeper in their reflections. So, that's about the breakout rooms, and with that, probably we can
Dr. Karan Mittal: go to…
Dr. Karan Mittal: what we are… what we mean to complete today. So, Prabhuji, I would request you to kind of…
GOVINDA Das: Oops.
Dr. Karan Mittal: People would listen.
GOVINDA Das: Thank you, joining with, again.
GOVINDA Das: So, yesterday, We overall discussed the… the modern psychology.
GOVINDA Das: with some touch of Dharmic or Indian perspective.
GOVINDA Das: One of the most important parts of belief in mind, It's based upon faith-centric ideas.
GOVINDA Das: Faith-centric ideas, basically, what do they do?
GOVINDA Das: They create an infrastructure, a frozen, tight infrastructure, in regards to our understanding about the mind, ego.
GOVINDA Das: Our interaction with the world.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, When we study… The faith-centric logic
GOVINDA Das: In regards to mind and hankar also.
GOVINDA Das: Then it becomes more and more clear.
GOVINDA Das: What the mind really needs is inner experience. What the mind often receives is outer compliance.
GOVINDA Das: This is very important, right? Our belief is formed not because we've explored.
GOVINDA Das: Our belief is formed because we have been imposed.
GOVINDA Das: We're not discussing right or wrong.
GOVINDA Das: How do we get to that belief?
GOVINDA Das: That belief is coming from the space of not exploration. It is coming from the space of imposition.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, when we study, The person who's practicing deeper spirituality
GOVINDA Das: They are more of an explorer rather than imposers.
GOVINDA Das: That means they are not forcing others to accept what they believe in.
GOVINDA Das: Faith and naturality. Now, faith is not necessarily natural. It can be natural.
GOVINDA Das: But not necessarily natural.
GOVINDA Das: Schwabi?
GOVINDA Das: Like, when you study creation, when you study the 15th, 16th, 17th century Europe.
GOVINDA Das: What was the contradiction? The contradiction between the time span of the creation According to the… the scriptures.
GOVINDA Das: And scientific progression.
GOVINDA Das: And because of that conflict, They started losing faith in what they had grown up.
GOVINDA Das: And that contradiction, there was a famous philosopher, Herbert Spencer, He says…
GOVINDA Das: Agnosticism is the beginning of inquiry. Now, agnosticism is not atheism.
GOVINDA Das: It is not pessimism. It is not negativity.
Lavina Shewaramani: My pink.
GOVINDA Das: stage of humility where you say, I do not know, but I want to learn.
GOVINDA Das: And that is very healthy for the mind. We will study that from the Buddhi perspective.
GOVINDA Das: Institutional belief system often replaced direct experience with ritual conformity and rules.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: the insta… Institutional belief. Institutional doesn't mean that we are talking about some organization.
GOVINDA Das: A religion is always institutionalized. Again, we are not discussing right or wrong.
GOVINDA Das: So there is a pattern which you are supposed to follow.
GOVINDA Das: When we follow this institutional belief.
GOVINDA Das: What does it do? It gives us more focus on the ritual than the experience.
GOVINDA Das: When meaning is not felt, but only performed, the psyche begins to look for it elsewhere.
GOVINDA Das: And that is where dependencies begin.
GOVINDA Das: Am I right?
GOVINDA Das: Then, when the meaning is not felt, we are not experiencing the meaning, Then what do we do?
GOVINDA Das: I'm dealing with few such people.
GOVINDA Das: Where they were aggressive in practice.
GOVINDA Das: But at some point of time, because the experience was not happening.
GOVINDA Das: they started looking elsewhere. Therefore, Carl Jung, he explains, Addiction.
GOVINDA Das: And belief in religion, if it is not properly managed, have the same impact.
GOVINDA Das: What is it? We lose the power of discretion. Next.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… So yesterday, when… when we were discussing about the Indic…
Dr. Karan Mittal: We spoke about COVID, and we discussed how faith in karma, faith in God, helps a person.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, when we see things from Indic perspective, it starts right from Atarva Veda up till Sushuta, Marshi Sushuta, that how faith or different, different, parameters that govern the faith can help in healing of a person.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And it's not that it went unnoticed in the Western psychology. Carl Jung basically
Dr. Karan Mittal: often, you know, because he had a good read of various Indic cultures or indigenous cultures, he often commented upon, or he wrote about, how religion can help a person in healing. But he also said that religion, as Poji said, that religion is something which should produce an inner experience.
Dr. Karan Mittal: it should not be a performance, it should not just be a ritual. It should bring about an inner experience. And when you have that substratum of that inner experience with the client, then if you use that substratum or that foundation in the healing of the client, the results are
Dr. Karan Mittal: magnanimous. But if religion or practices are just, you know, kind of… are just rotating around it being a ritual or a performance, and you use that
Dr. Karan Mittal: religion, or that particular meditation, chanting, or contemplative practice as a tool in your counseling, it won't give you results. In fact, it can put the client into a guilt trap.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Why do… maybe… why do some people can… some people benefit when they kind of associate themselves to a spiritual tradition, and some people don't?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Because if the spiritual tradition is taken in the correct spirit, then it helps you heal, it helps you have hope, it helps you have faith. But if it's taken in the negative way, or if many rules and restrictions are kind of imposed upon the person, then that same religion or that same spiritual practice can bring in guilt.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Can bring in depression, can bring in jealousy, comparison, and all the other things.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The same person who has addiction can use God or faith or spirituality to come out of that addiction, and the same person, if that faith is imposed in the wrong way, can feel guilty of being addict for 20 years, can feel depressed, that many people are, you know, are much better than me, are out of addiction, and I'm still struggling with my small, small, small, small attractions towards various
Dr. Karan Mittal: addictive potencies. So, Carl Jung said that religion can be used in psychological healing only if it brings in that inner experience. If it's a performance, if it's a ritual, we'll come to the four parameters that Jung said, that because most of us
Dr. Karan Mittal: probably bring to that spiritual, belong to that spiritual, bend of counseling. Also, if… even if we are normal, into normal, into normal psychology and counseling.
Dr. Karan Mittal: looking at faith and religion, like, I know a friend of mine, or probably a senior of mine, is doing a PhD thesis on need of God in psychotherapy.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, how God, the concept of God, or how belief or faith in God, can help a person come out of his psychological issues, and vice versa, how, if it's imposed in the wrong way, can push the person more into depression, jealousy, and guilt. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… So, feet?
Dr. Karan Mittal: sometimes being spiritual counselors, we need to understand when to use faith, when to use spiritual practices to help the client, and when to give that relaxation. So now, I'm just going a bit impromptu. In human body, there are two kinds of nervous systems.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? One nervous system is called as a sympathetic nervous system. I know I'm using a medical terminology, but it's a very simple terminology.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sympathetic nervous system is that part of your nervous system that works in flight, fight, fear. So whenever your body needs to work extra, whether it's running, whether it's fighting, whether it's fear or anxiety, the sympathetic nervous system becomes active.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And parasympathetic nervous system is the nervous system of meditation, of… of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: healing, of going deeper, of relaxation. So that's the parasympathetic nervous system. Now, imagine religious practices or spiritual practices that need to activate the parasympathetic nervous system, that is relaxation, calmness, etc, are now activating the sympathetic nervous system. A person is so stressed about waking up at 4am in the morning, doing his particular practices, then rushing to the office, then being so very rigid about
Dr. Karan Mittal: food and other things that he or she tries to follow. That instead of healing or calming or, you know, probably providing that transformative experience to the person, the person is living a mechanical life where every practice is becoming like a sympathetic activation for the person.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And that's the aim of yoga, that's the aim of pranayim, that's the aim of all the spiritual practices, that this parasympathetic nervous system should be active.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's where… that's where, as counselors, we need to segregate, where to… where to kind of use that spiritual practice in the counseling therapy, and where to kind of take a step back and let… let not… let's not impose that spiritual practice on the person to induce more guilt and depression.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… So this is what…
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, when the faith heals, it produces that inner, genuine experience, as probably you said, so it is transformative. You find that happiness, you find that euphoria, you find that pleasure when you are doing those exercises.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Even in the faith, even in that spiritual practice, some people might find faith in medi… sorry, peace or happiness in meditation. Some might find peace and happiness in seva, some might find peace and happiness in dressing, or other kinds of religious activities. So you need to find out which
Dr. Karan Mittal: which activity actually activates that transformative experience for your client? You cannot… the rules are a separate thing, but the transformative activity becomes a separate thing.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And…
Dr. Karan Mittal: When the faith harms, or when the faith is imposed in the wrong way, then you try to kind of… that… that…
Dr. Karan Mittal: that particular activity, instead of becoming an inner experience, just becomes a compliance, or just becomes a performance, or just becomes an ego-boosting thing. You know many people who have been… who have been into various kind of spiritual traditions, practicing for years and decades, and still
Dr. Karan Mittal: struggling with the… struggling with their ego, or struggling with the compliance, or struggling with finding meaning in the spiritual practice. So that's where the difference comes in. Now, suppose a person who's not feeling
Dr. Karan Mittal: that inner transformation in those two hours of his spiritual practice. If that person comes to you, and you tell him, okay, go into the shelter of that spiritual practice again, will it yield any results?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, you'll have to kind of take a step back and see what practice actually can make him feel that happiness and euphoria and peace, and then prescribe accordingly.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. So, I'm not getting into the whole… all the four points in each of the tables, we'll come to it in detail when we see the next slides, but Jung basically had four, you know, kind of criteria to
Dr. Karan Mittal: as a counselor or as a therapist, to understand whether I should intervene in this person's spiritual practice or faith? Should I be asking questions? Should I be kind of suggesting any maneuvers or measures? Or should I take a step back and concentrate just on my part? The first is experience or performance.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Whichever tradition the client belongs to, asking them which
Dr. Karan Mittal: Is the practice giving you some inner happiness, or it has just become a performance, a mechanical ritual that you have been doing for years? When was the last time you felt
Dr. Karan Mittal: happy? When was the last time you kind of connected with the DT that you are focusing on, or with the goal that you're focusing on in spirituality? So that's the first thing that you understand, whether he's doing… sometimes
Dr. Karan Mittal: spiritual people kind of create a mask, or create an aura around themselves, that they are so, so spiritual, they are so, so, you know, they follow discipline. So there are many, many labels that get associated with people who are following the spiritual disciplines very strictly.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Are these labels kind of transforming something within?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's the first thing about that. The layer 2, opening or narrowing. Many people come to me that… so, so many people come to me that they belong to a particular spiritual tradition, and they don't interact with any other person that belongs to another spiritual tradition, because it corrupts their mind. Now, suppose this person himself is going through
Dr. Karan Mittal: probably depression, or through social inhibitions. Sometimes the spiritual rules are like a bypass, or are like just a defense for their inner inhibition, and they say that, okay, we are not allowed to interact with that particular group of people.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, are they… are there rules? Is there heart? Is there… are there mind? Is it opening up, or is it narrowing down because of that spiritual practice? Integrating or bypassing? Most of the time in therapy, when we, you know, talk to people who have been in spiritual traditions for a very long period of time, they have bypasses.
Dr. Karan Mittal: They talk about an incident 20 years ago that affected them, and 20 years later, when they are in the session, they talk about forgiveness.
Dr. Karan Mittal: They talk about the law of karma, but is the emotion that was associated with that 20-year-old incident healed?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Is the anger healed? Frustration healed? Is the jealousy healed? So, spiritual rules of forgiveness, karma, sometimes can be used as bypasses into therapy. People try to, like, I… because I'm also into regression work, etc, people try to
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, kind of avoid the present issue, and then try to find a metaphor or related situation in the past, because that's easier to deal.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Something 10 years ago, 15 years ago, is easier to talk about rather than what's happening today.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so bypassing is a very common thing that you will see in people who practice any spiritual tradition, and mobilizing or paralyzed. Like, I have
Dr. Karan Mittal: I have a client who belongs to a particular school of thought, and she told me that I should focus more on Seva, I should leave my job, because if the God has to provide, the money will come from any particular need. I'm dealing with this client currently. My question to her was.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Is it because you really believe in this law? Is it because you believe about your… is it because you kind of have problems with the performance at the office or in your workspace? So that was the issue. She was not able to perform well in the area she was working in, and then she started using this virtual
Dr. Karan Mittal: law or spiritual saying or instruction to bypass that particular inhibition of hers, or fear of hers, or anxiety of hers. So we have to see that whether the spiritual tradition is really helping the person move forward.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or they're just using the laws or the instructions to paralyze themselves in a particular area of their work. So these were the four questions that, particularly if you're dealing with a person coming from a specific spiritual practice, two years or 3 years or more.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course, for new people, these all questions might not hold true, but if they have been a practice for more than three years, then asking these questions, even if you don't want to ask, just contemplating or indirectly asking these questions give you deeper insights. And if the answer to all the four layers are the positive ones, like experience, opening, integrating, and mobilizing, then you don't get into the
Dr. Karan Mittal: into the spiritual dimension of that person. You focus on proper counseling and psychological
Dr. Karan Mittal: If any of the answers are kind of… suppose if the person is bypassing,
Dr. Karan Mittal: A particular memory, then you encourage the client to get into that particular memory, and then work on the anger, jealousy, etc, to achieve the results.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Bruce.
GOVINDA Das: Yes.
GOVINDA Das: So, as we were discussing, very interesting point, what Karanji explained.
GOVINDA Das: Alright?
GOVINDA Das: One should write it down, because…
GOVINDA Das: It is not only asking others this question.
GOVINDA Das: Asking ourselves also this question, because…
GOVINDA Das: The beauty of spirituality is that it makes one extremely sincere.
GOVINDA Das: And one of the quality of sincerity is that
GOVINDA Das: Some sincerity in regards to practice.
GOVINDA Das: But because there is a sincerity of practice, One loses to be authentic.
GOVINDA Das: Because when you become authentic, there is an element of questioning your own sincerity.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, these questions which Dr. Curran raised are extremely important.
GOVINDA Das: It will not take one away from their spiritual practice. The purpose of Indian knowledge system is to provide an integral
GOVINDA Das: Contribution to one's own growth and others' growth.
GOVINDA Das: Anna, Prada, Mano, Vikyan, and Anand Maikosh. So there is no question of that. In fact, the modern psychology
GOVINDA Das: Many times, Because using this principle of because you're too sincere, therefore you are feeling guilty.
GOVINDA Das: They ask their clients to give up their spiritual practice.
GOVINDA Das: So that you can be free from the guilt.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: So, if you are free from the guilt.
GOVINDA Das: How do you become free from the guilt?
GOVINDA Das: They attack the very practice which has caused you to become guilty according to them.
GOVINDA Das: So therefore, this was very profound for sutras Dr. Karanji offered us.
GOVINDA Das: And now, based upon that only, when we are deeply authentic and sincere practicing spirituality.
GOVINDA Das: Especially the concept of religion here, religion. What does it do?
GOVINDA Das: There is a famous neuroscientist, a public intellectual.
GOVINDA Das: He's an atheist, but he's a spiritualist.
GOVINDA Das: Believes in Indian idea. He wrote a book called As End of Faith.
GOVINDA Das: I read that book, after reading that book, I became more deeper into my spiritual practice.
GOVINDA Das: It is called as End of Faith.
GOVINDA Das: But if someone who does not have proper idea reads that book, they'll give complete spiritual practice, because it is written extremely deep.
GOVINDA Das: And these are the 5 ideas he presents in his book.
GOVINDA Das: One is empathy.
GOVINDA Das: What does belief do? Belief overrides empathy.
GOVINDA Das: When you see somebody suffering, like, recently someone was… Had a broken limb.
GOVINDA Das: You know, he broke his… he broke his knee.
GOVINDA Das: Then he met one of his spiritual friend. That spiritual friend said, after all, everybody has to suffer their karma.
GOVINDA Das: Alright.
GOVINDA Das: Now, that is not a very good statement.
GOVINDA Das: There is no empathy. The power of empathy is that… the power of non-empathy is that the radicalized person are not necessary.
GOVINDA Das: earthly monsters.
GOVINDA Das: They're psychologically normal only, but the problem is… When someone truly believes.
GOVINDA Das: that violence is divinely commanded. Now, violence not necessarily means you have to kill people.
GOVINDA Das: You can be violent verbally also.
GOVINDA Das: You do not take their suffering to be their suffering, but you philosophize their suffering.
GOVINDA Das: And become less sensitive to their suffering.
GOVINDA Das: This is one of the greatest tragedy of people practicing religion on the superficial level.
GOVINDA Das: They lack empathy.
GOVINDA Das: Second, the certainty.
GOVINDA Das: You know, in the… in the… any holy scriptures, of the Bharatiya literature.
GOVINDA Das: whether you are a Bhakta like Mirabhaye, or the great Authar Lord Chaitanya, what was their idea? Their idea was that, I don't know Krishna.
GOVINDA Das: Right.
GOVINDA Das: One who knows Krishna, he knows everything, but who knows Krishna, he says, I don't know Krishna.
GOVINDA Das: If you take the Vedanta Sutra, or you take the Bhagavat Purana, one of the core principles is that, I do not know.
GOVINDA Das: Socrates said, I am the… I am not mature. I know that I know nothing.
GOVINDA Das: The Keno Upanishad explains What is the… what is the, difference between Guru and Shisha? Very profound.
GOVINDA Das: The difference between Guru and Shisha is that Guru knows
GOVINDA Das: That he or she does not know.
GOVINDA Das: And Shisha does not know that he…
GOVINDA Das: He or she does not know.
GOVINDA Das: The power of religion is that it actually destroys all your inquiry.
GOVINDA Das: It makes one so superficially confident
GOVINDA Das: Even those subjects where they are not expert, they will start giving commentary on that.
GOVINDA Das: That is what the second point he mentions.
GOVINDA Das: Third is afterlife.
GOVINDA Das: What does afterlife do? Changes risk calculation.
GOVINDA Das: Now, afterlife is very important, according to the,
GOVINDA Das: You know, the Hindu tradition, or the traditional Egyptian tradition.
GOVINDA Das: When you know that there is something after life, I am not Shunya, I will not be lost, it gives some relief. That is good in the Satva Guddha.
GOVINDA Das: But imagine that…
GOVINDA Das: when you are completely clear that I don't want to be part of this world, this world is useless place.
GOVINDA Das: I can do any amount of violence, because after death, everything will be over. There was a prime minister or president of Sri Lanka.
GOVINDA Das: He was killed by a Buddhist monk.
GOVINDA Das: That naturally, he was caught, and he was about to be given a death penalty.
GOVINDA Das: And during his… Just a few days before he was supposed to be hanged.
GOVINDA Das: a preacher came to him, a Christian preacher, he said, you…
GOVINDA Das: take to the path of Christianity, Jesus will free you from all the sin.
GOVINDA Das: Right? You will not come back to this world.
GOVINDA Das: After the judgment day, you'll go back to the kingdom if you take shelter.
GOVINDA Das: So what does it do?
GOVINDA Das: That makes a person who has committed the crime
GOVINDA Das: to be free of the mentality of Prayish Chitta.
GOVINDA Das: And artificially, he or she feels that now I don't need to… I don't need to do anything about this. Therefore.
GOVINDA Das: Imagine if you talk to the jihadis, They're simple children.
GOVINDA Das: When they're trained to see that there is nothing but only further opportunity Living a responsible life.
GOVINDA Das: Becomes redundant to them.
GOVINDA Das: Alright, and then cult, or a group. What does it do? It amplifies moral blindness at the cost of nyaya.
GOVINDA Das: One of the beauty of Sanat and Dharma, is that your shraddha.
GOVINDA Das: can never be blind because there is a niaya also. The word is shraddha. The root word of shraddha comes from Satya.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: Because it comes from Satya, it cannot give rise to moral blindness. The reason logic can never be given up.
GOVINDA Das: But here, when there is a group.
GOVINDA Das: And the group is amplifying the same principle and again and again, you stop questioning.
GOVINDA Das: And therefore, ideas must be questioned.
GOVINDA Das: Take the Bhagavatam, take the Upanishad, take the, Puranas.
GOVINDA Das: Even in the Mahabharat, Draupadi questioned Krishna.
GOVINDA Das: How, my dear Krishna, I was almost abused by the gurus, and my husbands were watching.
GOVINDA Das: Right? In the Abrahamic religion, you cannot question anything which is the scriptural.
GOVINDA Das: Sripad Shankar, Shangrachara explains.
GOVINDA Das: If the scriptures say, the scriptures will not say like that. If the scriptures say, the fire does not burn.
GOVINDA Das: Water does not quench your thirst.
GOVINDA Das: But what is your experience? Your experience is that water actually quenches your thirst.
GOVINDA Das: Fire does one.
GOVINDA Das: So then he says, whom do you follow? You follow Prateksha Pramana?
GOVINDA Das: the word of the Scripture.
GOVINDA Das: He gives this logic, but certainly because it is simply an assumption, because scriptures do not speak like this.
GOVINDA Das: If they do, you have to follow the Pratakksha Pramana, you have to question the ideas. Only when you question the ideas, you do not become doubtful. Rather, you become deeper in your exploration of spiritual or religious practice. And therefore, faith
GOVINDA Das: without empathy, Faith, without inquiry, Faith, without focusing on life here also, Faith.
GOVINDA Das: Without questioning the group, and faith without questioning the ideas is dangerous as dangerous as faithlessness.
Dr. Karan Mittal: 2… So, time for an exercise, probably, since we're working on beliefs.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And yesterday, some people kind of had some struggle with coming down to a single belief about mine.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So today, I would request you to kind of pick up any one single belief.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That you have about mind, consciousness, soul, self, body, anything, anything that concerns you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, about your habits, about yourself. Just reflect on one particular belief.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then, in the breakout room, the opposite person will try to peel this out. So this is the first skill that we learn as counselors. It's called a Socratic questioning, where we try to find the origin, or try to find where did this belief originate from.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, of course, it's a very complex scale, it requires different kinds of questioning, but today we'll kind of just stay with this question, how do you know?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, suppose I say that, that…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, I'm not the human body, I'm the soul. So, so, the opposite person asks me, how do you know? So, I'll say that I heard it in a lecture 10 years ago.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so, so, that's the question, okay? So, how do you know it was correct? So, probably there was a quotation from a scripture. So, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, how do you know it is correct? So, my answer will end over there, because I feel the scripture is correct.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I have believed that what the lecturer said was true, and therefore I have this belief within me. So, this is just going a few steps deeper about that particular belief, and then trying to get to the root where did this belief originate for you. It could probably related, you know, you can probably bring to your mind that age.
Dr. Karan Mittal: that scenario when this belief starts for you. And then, for your self-contemplation, you contemplate how did this belief affect you in the last few years. So, probably, I'll give you 12, 12 minutes like yesterday.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And of course, I'll also hop in, Probably will also hop into different breakout rooms. But… but this is for more… this is for you to, as a therapist, to experience Socratic questioning.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And as a client, to start going deeper into different beliefs of yours. And I would say, pick up an uncomfortable belief. Don't pick up something like what I picked up, because then you… you don't have
Dr. Karan Mittal: You don't go deeper, actually, you're just playing around with your mind. So go with an uncomfortable belief, and see how it works. So I'll just give you a few minutes, until I organize the breakout rooms to come up with a belief.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And in a minute or two, I'll initiate the breakout rooms.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, I hope everybody understood any… any doubt people have.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, if you have any doubts, please, please ask.
suraj racha: Yes, currently, can you actually repeat, what exactly to do? I mean, Vortex?
GOVINDA Das: We can do a role play. We can do a role play. Karan, I will ask you a question. You tell me what it is.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Excuse me.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah. Yes, so, I'll have to just,
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so I'll pick up the belief that I picked up last time, so it's easier for people to understand. So, I have a belief that mind is a mechanical thing, and it can be tamed easily about my mind.
GOVINDA Das: Okay, so you say the mind is a mechanical thing, it can be tamed easily.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Easily, yeah.
GOVINDA Das: Where did you get this knowledge from?
Dr. Karan Mittal: I think I heard it from my father when I was a child.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so I think at around 7-8 years old, I heard it from my father, and then I started… yeah, I'm believing that thing, yeah.
GOVINDA Das: But how do your father say that? Is he a scientist?
GOVINDA Das: What is a spiritualist?
Dr. Karan Mittal: No, he's not.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And…
GOVINDA Das: So, how do you believe that?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah. So I believed him because he's a… he was my… he's my father, so, like, Shabda Pramana, and as a 7-8 year old, I took it very seriously because he kind of conditioned me to kind of believe that mind can be tamed, and wake up at a particular time, do this, do that.
Dr. Karan Mittal: develop a schedule. There's nothing called as laziness. And it also, in reflection, it tells me.
Dr. Karan Mittal: how harsh, you know, the first… like, the first few years in my teenage, I was on myself, my body, etc, trying to be very…
Dr. Karan Mittal: And even now, I'm very harsh with my schedule, and very, sometimes I don't give myself a scope of
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, loosening my schedule and discipline, yeah.
GOVINDA Das: That worked for you, but most time it does not work. People become rebellious because of this kind of practices.
GOVINDA Das: Is it not?
Dr. Karan Mittal: If I… yeah, if I see it very deeply today, it has not worked for me. It has given me immense stress, rather than that, you know, that comfort. Of course, it has worked in material sense, but internally, it has been a… it has been a heavy belief for me, too.
GOVINDA Das: Like this, like this, you have to break the person who is answering.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, so I hope this is clear, I guess.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah.
suraj racha: Yes, yes, yes, thank you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, but just as part… as counselors, just be gentle, don't… don't get into that judge's role and just, you know, be harsh with the client. Yeah, okay, okay, I'll just open up the breakup.
GOVINDA Das: You can do 3 questions, no? Like, 3 to 4 times.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, 3 to 4 times, yes. We'll keep it flexible. Yes, sir.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I don't know.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, I'm opening the rooms. You can join the rooms.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If you don't join.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Listen.
A-Mridul Sharma: Sorry.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Honeywell.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
A-Mridul Sharma: Did, should…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Radhuji, I have not assigned you any room. Would you like to participate?
A-Mridul Sharma: No, no, no, it's okay, yeah, fine.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
A-Mridul Sharma: Actually, I couldn't join the yesterday's call, so I think I…
A-Mridul Sharma: Yeah, yeah, go through the recording also, so that's why I think I should not participate.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Oh, sure. If you want to go as a, just an observer, that… but anyways, we'll check it later. Yes.
A-Mridul Sharma: Yeah, it's a…
A-Mridul Sharma: So I should be staying here, or should I leave?
shubham singh: Not yet.
shubham singh: Saudi Art!
Dr. Karan Mittal: How was it for you, Ruthujaji? I think I couldn't join your group.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sorry, I'm not able to hear you, you're on mute.
Rutuja Nayak: Am I audible now?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, you're audible.
Rutuja Nayak: is.
Rutuja Nayak: It was good, actually, Sneha and I were in this room, so…
Rutuja Nayak: Actually, we didn't have much questions. Guruji had joined our chat group.
Rutuja Nayak: So I… I had this belief of, it's all about choices you make in your life. So she asked me, where did you get this choice? I said, it's my uncle, and why? And then it was purely based on my experiences, other than anything else.
Rutuja Nayak: So, yeah, that's what… and we both had similar things, we both had beliefs, but because of our own experiences. That's what we discussed.
Rutuja Nayak: And I don't… so yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, welcome back, everyone.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I was there in a few breakout rooms, and I think many of you could have… could go 3 layers, at least, deep, to the belief, which is a good start, like, you know.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course, when we do Socratic questioning, sometimes we go 8, 9, 10 layers deeper, but 3 to 4 layers to begin with. So basically, focus on the 3, you know, what, where, when, why, how.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, how sometimes is very transformative, that… how did it impact your life? How did it change things for you? If that belief wasn't there, how would your life be different?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So these questions kind of trigger something, kind of stimulate something inside the client. So you don't need to be… and also, some of you were very, you know, like.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Cut to cut, like, the client stops speaking, and then you ask another question. Let the client assimilate it a bit, and then you ask another question. Maybe in your mind, you already have five questions, but that assimilation, that shunyatta in between is important for the questions to penetrate deeper.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And probably the second part of it, which you need to do individually, is for the belief that you picked up. Sorry, Prabhuji, this is… yeah.
GOVINDA Das: Yep.
GOVINDA Das: So, as I…
GOVINDA Das: also went through different rooms. You know, there is so much of diversity in regards to, you know, different kinds of belief. You know, it's very interesting. You know, it could be religious, it could be just natural experiences of life.
GOVINDA Das: just now I was in one room where, you know,
GOVINDA Das: You know, same belief system can have a different perspective.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Different Dishtiko.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Somebody may have a particular belief system. Even I may have that particular belief system.
GOVINDA Das: But may have a different, totally opposite perspective for the very same belief system.
GOVINDA Das: There is a diversity of belief system, and there are millions of perspective for that very, you know, belief system also. Somebody…
GOVINDA Das: Could be very sincere.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, right?
GOVINDA Das: And they may find that that sincerity has not benefited them as much It should have benefited.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Somebody has a very positive understanding of people. Oh, there are limitless potential.
GOVINDA Das: So that limitless potential.
GOVINDA Das: For some people, it gives rise to hope perpetually, because you believe that they have potential.
GOVINDA Das: And for some people, it may say, Ithna patients, when will you… when will you exhibit that potential, right? It is so fascinating, it is so amazing. You know, it's not that this one is right, or that one is right.
GOVINDA Das: It is… it is ultimately to see whether such belief system is helping me to grow, or getting me stuck into that very system.
GOVINDA Das: It was a great exercise.
GOVINDA Das: Good to see. So, the irony of faith
GOVINDA Das: Right? The… another interesting principle of Bharati, which are the Indian Knowledge System.
GOVINDA Das: It is called as the duality, dwandua.
GOVINDA Das: Right? In the Mahabharat, one of the most fascinating discussion happens between Yujishthin and Arjun.
GOVINDA Das: And one… Point Arjuna tells you this to the Maharaj.
GOVINDA Das: He says, my dear brother, in this world.
GOVINDA Das: There is nothing which is completely positive.
GOVINDA Das: And he says, there is nothing which is completely negative.
GOVINDA Das: Every positive has a seed of negativity.
GOVINDA Das: And every negativity has the seed of positivity.
GOVINDA Das: Very important to understand this principle. Nothing in this world which is completely positive.
GOVINDA Das: even the Amrita, became death to Rahu and Ketu.
GOVINDA Das: And the poison for Bhima, Gave him the strength of 10,000 elephants.
GOVINDA Das: He was sped poison by Duryodhan, and he was thrown into the water. He was… he landed into Nagaloka, and the snakes in the Nagaloka, they bit him.
GOVINDA Das: So rather than dying by the bite of the snake, it becomes antidote.
GOVINDA Das: Alright?
GOVINDA Das: Now, it may be… it may be a story.
GOVINDA Das: But if you see, apply this logic in every aspect of life.
GOVINDA Das: There is nothing which gives rise to complete positivity or complete negativity.
GOVINDA Das: Similarly fit… Faith without dharma… It's like a gambling match.
GOVINDA Das: Alright? I remember talking to one couple, And the husband told me…
GOVINDA Das: You know, the path of spirituality which I chose, it has made me a human being.
GOVINDA Das: And the path which my wife
GOVINDA Das: chose, same path they chose, both of them, they chose the same path. For a man, it became very beneficial, but for a wife, it ruined her progressive life.
GOVINDA Das: It was very interesting when I heard that first time.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, when we study the irony of faith is…
GOVINDA Das: Like, they say, what is the distinction between genius and a madman?
GOVINDA Das: It is a thin line difference. Similarly, faith is like that.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Faith is extremely beneficial At the same time, it is dangerous beyond limit.
GOVINDA Das: we have to reflect… we have to reflect upon this. You know, you see many places…
GOVINDA Das: That when you… when you see, when you study the stories of The… the extreme religious ideas
GOVINDA Das: how much they have become responsible for destroying people, killing people, in the name of religion, brutally, including their varied parents. I remember listening to one, one, BBC
GOVINDA Das: conversation where the group of people were asked about, what if your parents do not take to the path of
GOVINDA Das: the teaching what you have taken. They were asking a girl.
GOVINDA Das: What will happen to them? The girl said they will go to hell.
GOVINDA Das: So the anchor Aster Are you serious?
GOVINDA Das: That the parents who raised you nicely, they give you education, they may not be practicing what you practice.
GOVINDA Das: You are confident that they'll go to hell?
GOVINDA Das: She said, yes, if they don't practice what I practice, because this is the highest in life.
GOVINDA Das: You know, it doesn't matter even if they're their parents, I love them, but their destination is health.
GOVINDA Das: the great Shivaji Maharaj.
GOVINDA Das: Right? After his departure, One of the priests wrote to the Portuguese queen. That letter is actually recorded.
GOVINDA Das: Glorifying all the good qualities of Shivaji Maharaj.
GOVINDA Das: But what is the conclusion of that letter? The conclusion of that letter is, because he practiced the pagan religion, he has to go to the hell.
GOVINDA Das: Imagine, right, you're glorifying good qualities, but in your mind, you are sending them to hell.
GOVINDA Das: So there… it is extremely beneficial, it is dangerous beyond limit, therefore what Arjuna said is an extremely important, therefore one has to think critically.
GOVINDA Das: Thinking critically becomes… thinking critically does not mean acting.
GOVINDA Das: In the way of slandering and criticizing, think critically, Feel naturally.
GOVINDA Das: Like, in one of the rooms, One participant explained.
GOVINDA Das: that I also need a me time. There is a mother time, and there is a me time also.
GOVINDA Das: Now, how many mothers actually think about me time?
GOVINDA Das: They don't.
GOVINDA Das: Right? They… in fact, those thoughts of me time, especially we're talking about, maybe 20, 30 years ago, thinking about me time was non-existent.
GOVINDA Das: At least nowadays, people are at least thinking about me time, because thinking me time for a mother
GOVINDA Das: Was seen as an extremely artificial and selfish thing to do.
GOVINDA Das: Their identity as me was completely destroyed. Her identity was only a mother.
GOVINDA Das: Right? So, this is an artificial reality.
GOVINDA Das: So, think critically, Feel naturally and act strategically.
GOVINDA Das: That is what gives rise to healthy shraddha, which is deeper.
GOVINDA Das: Which is inner experience, and creates a profound vibration to those In our surrounding.
GOVINDA Das: Next.
GOVINDA Das: Yep.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Who?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Since we… since we worked on a belief.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And now we start peeling down the belief. Now, this isn't something that you do for yourself, there's no breakout room.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Therefore, questions that you need to ask yourselves about the belief.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Does this belief allow me to doubt it?
Dr. Karan Mittal: If no, then, of course, maybe you could just ask, answer the questions for yourself, and then we'll discuss it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Does it require me to see others as inferior? Like, in one of the breakout rooms, someone said that
Dr. Karan Mittal: I have certain beliefs about following certain principles, spiritual and religious principles. And people who don't follow it, I look at them in a judgmental way. I look at them as inferiors, I look at them as not disciplined. So, does that belief make you look at others as inferior?
Dr. Karan Mittal: does it produce an inner experience, or really outer compliance, like what we discussed in Jung and religion? That… is that belief really helping you transform within, or you're now just doing it mechanically as a compliance thing, and then feeling superior about following those principles?
Dr. Karan Mittal: And could I still hold it without a group reinforcement? So if you were not
Dr. Karan Mittal: with the people who are following that belief, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: would you still follow that belief with that same conviction? If not, then you're dependent on that group.
Dr. Karan Mittal: To kind of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: follow that belief. I usually, when we work with beliefs, that we be… I call it as the Hiranda Kashifra of Kaluga, we kind of try seeing things as black and white, as dualities, but we don't understand that it's a multicolor, world, and it's a multicolor mind.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, there's a continuum that exists between white and black, between yes and no. And sometimes when we are rigidly associated with one particular belief, we try to impose that belief on others, we try to make that belief harsh for ourselves, we try to kind of impose it on our family, that kind of spoils the relationship with our family, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So someone said that he has a particular belief about religious principles, and he tries, and he expects that from the family.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And when he expects that from the family, it kind of hampers the relationship between him and parents, kids, wife, etc.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Another client of mine who follows a spiritual tradition married a particular person with the condition that he will also switch into the spiritual tradition eventually.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And one of the…
Dr. Karan Mittal: reasons of their couples counseling, the reasons that they came to me for couples counseling, is that the man was not able to switch.
Dr. Karan Mittal: to that particular belief system, because of whatever experiences you have later. So, these are the four questions that you ask yourself about any belief, or
Dr. Karan Mittal: Any… you ask the counselee or the client in front of you, where do they stand with the belief system?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, we'll come to these four questions later, and how it impacts us, probably in the Session 3, but just, I want you to dwell on these
Dr. Karan Mittal: Three, four questions, and see where the answer is no, and where the answer is a yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: privileging.
GOVINDA Das: ills… So… One of the, again, one of the disadvantages of faith tradition.
GOVINDA Das: We'll come to Dharma tradition.
GOVINDA Das: The faith tradition, which is… More about practicing sultan rituals, Systems?
GOVINDA Das: And hard beliefs, what do they do?
GOVINDA Das: Here, where the theology runs out.
GOVINDA Das: Mind is discussed metaphorically, not systematically.
GOVINDA Das: Spirit, soul, heart, all are blurred together.
GOVINDA Das: In fact, if you ask… if you ask some of the
GOVINDA Das: Best scholars of the faith-centric religion.
GOVINDA Das: they do not have proper explanation about it. They might discuss about function.
GOVINDA Das: But the explanation is not there, and therefore, in the 15th, 16th century.
GOVINDA Das: When people were suffering because of the mental health, that was seen as a sin rather than seen as a disease.
GOVINDA Das: They were ostracized. Just like in India, there was, you know, untouchability. There are huge stories.
GOVINDA Das: one, IT person, he wrote a book on mind in a Marathi, it's in a Marathi book, it's a Marathi book.
GOVINDA Das: And he explains, giving the full history about
GOVINDA Das: People is to go to see mad people paying tickets.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Because… Imagine this was in the European country.
GOVINDA Das: There were chairs.
GOVINDA Das: They would think that because their mind is not proper, it is not spinning properly, they would be put in a moving chair, and it would move so hard.
GOVINDA Das: And sometimes they put them upside down, sometimes actually remove blood from their body.
GOVINDA Das: Why? Because they felt that they've offended the higher spirit, It is a sin
GOVINDA Das: On the other hand, Ayurved does not see it as a sin, it sees it as a disease. It is not papa, it is Roka.
GOVINDA Das: No consistent model of mental functioning exists across theological tradition.
GOVINDA Das: You take many traditions. In fact, in one aspect of Christianity, It is seen as…
GOVINDA Das: The birth of a woman itself is a mistake.
GOVINDA Das: No? It is seen as a mistake.
GOVINDA Das: Another tradition, when somebody's… Lame, somebody's tum, somebody's blind.
GOVINDA Das: It is considered as fractured soul.
GOVINDA Das: Just like the body is fractured, similarly, the soul is fractured.
GOVINDA Das: And there are some traditions, they say, you know, some souls will perpetually rot in hell.
GOVINDA Das: And some soul will perpetually go to the spiritual realm.
GOVINDA Das: I remember reading some comment on, when Divine Comedy came out.
GOVINDA Das: Dante, he wrote that book. He had a great appreciation for Socrates.
GOVINDA Das: But Socrates came before Jesus Christ.
GOVINDA Das: Now, where do you send Socrates?
GOVINDA Das: Right? You cannot achieve perfection without the grace of Jesus.
GOVINDA Das: But at the same time, you're such an infatu- in such an impact about Socrates, you don't want to send him to hellish planet.
GOVINDA Das: So then there was a divine purgative.
GOVINDA Das: Right? There was some neutral system was created, neither hell or nor heaven.
GOVINDA Das: Otherwise, in this tradition, there are only two things. You go to hell, or you go to heaven.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, The… the theology of mind is extremely abstract.
GOVINDA Das: The religious beliefs are extremely concrete.
GOVINDA Das: Believes are concrete, but the definition of mind is extremely abstract and confusing.
GOVINDA Das: The brain is revered, but not back. Honored, not understood.
GOVINDA Das: Mental illness is often reduced to sin, possession, or destiny.
GOVINDA Das: Moral categories, not functional ones. As I said this, this was one of the greatest tragedy created in the… eventually, now it is… Europe is very progressive, but in those times.
GOVINDA Das: Any kind of mental health was considered as proper, and here, sin.
GOVINDA Das: Is basically, unless you take shelter of faith.
GOVINDA Das: You cannot heal. But the problem is, if you have a… if you have a dental pain.
GOVINDA Das: It doesn't matter how sincerely you take to the path of spirituality.
GOVINDA Das: You cannot overcome that pain.
GOVINDA Das: Mind is also matter, like a tooth only, but much more subtle, as Karan was mentioning.
GOVINDA Das: Sometime you may have… you may have to separately deal with the mine.
GOVINDA Das: Sometime you have to deal with, on a physical level.
GOVINDA Das: And sometime you have to deal with a neurological damage.
GOVINDA Das: Now, this is very important.
GOVINDA Das: Alright?
GOVINDA Das: The whole foundation of Indic knowledge lies on these three principles.
GOVINDA Das: Satya Dharma Rutta.
GOVINDA Das: And there is Sharata.
GOVINDA Das: In the Bhagavatam Third Kento, there is a beautiful explanation of marriage of Dharma.
GOVINDA Das: When Dharma is married to Shraddha, what does it do? It gives rise to auspiciousness.
GOVINDA Das: If Dharma is not married to Sharadha, if Sharadha is not married to Dharma, what does it do? Dharma without Sharadha gives rise to inauspiciousness.
GOVINDA Das: It gives rise to violence. It gives rise to separatism. It gives rise to one of the saddest parts. I remember I was attending an interfaith conference.
GOVINDA Das: And those are devout spiritualists.
GOVINDA Das: If you ask them this question, what is greater? Your faith is greater?
GOVINDA Das: or your nation is greater.
GOVINDA Das: what do they say? Generally, they say, no, we don't care for Rashtra. For us, faith is greater.
GOVINDA Das: But if you study carefully, the Hindu scripture, there is no contradiction.
GOVINDA Das: Faith is my inner journey.
GOVINDA Das: And Rastra is my external loyalty. They are not in contradiction to each other.
GOVINDA Das: I don't have to create a contradiction between the two. Therefore, the question is, what is Dharma? You know, if anybody wants to, in one sentence, you know, whatever you understand, what is Dharma is?
GOVINDA Das: As I said, Dharma is not faith. Dharma is not ritual. Dharma is not belief.
GOVINDA Das: Because this is the foundation of Indian knowledge system.
GOVINDA Das: Dharma, Shraddha, Satya, and Rhuta.
GOVINDA Das: And especially Daraba.
GOVINDA Das: Now, those who have some understanding some assumption about Dharba.
GOVINDA Das: Now, what do you think about what is Dharma?
Lavina Shewaramani: Abush, can I say?
Lavina Shewaramani: Yes?
GOVINDA Das: Love energy?
Lavina Shewaramani: Right.
Lavina Shewaramani: Doing the right thing. Righteousness.
GOVINDA Das: Doing the right.
GOVINDA Das: Okay, doing righteousness.
Aarti Ganesh: That doesn't change with circumstance.
GOVINDA Das: Okay.
shubham singh: Term is the eternal law… eternal law and order.
GOVINDA Das: Eternal Land Auto, yes.
GOVINDA Das: Yes? Anything else?
suraj racha: The most navigable order in which one can function.
GOVINDA Das: Aji, what is that?
suraj racha: The most natural order.
suraj racha: Universal natural order in which one can function.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah.
GOVINDA Das: So, all… all answers are right.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: But when you study deeply, generally what happens, we consider our belief system as the greatest dharma.
GOVINDA Das: We all give these different answers.
GOVINDA Das: But generally, when we interact with the people, especially if you're a spiritual practitioner, your belief becomes the highest dharma, at the cost of isolating everyone, everybody else having a different belief system.
GOVINDA Das: So, we make Dharma synonymous to belief system, so let us try to understand.
GOVINDA Das: Not everything in Indian thought depends on belief.
GOVINDA Das: In fact, we do not begin with belief. We begin with Dharma. What is that? Dharma is the natural laws of life.
GOVINDA Das: unchangeable.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: Shraddha is a personal conviction, very subjective.
GOVINDA Das: I remember talking to about 50 students, On the day of Janmastery, Alright, so… the question was…
GOVINDA Das: whether do I believe Krishna existed or not?
GOVINDA Das: If they say, I don't believe Krishna existed, I said, can you prove that?
GOVINDA Das: They said, we cannot prove, just like you cannot prove the existence of God, specifically Krishna Ram. How do you prove?
GOVINDA Das: The judgment given by the court in regards to Raham Temple, that…
GOVINDA Das: They did not say this was the birthplace of Lord Ram.
GOVINDA Das: Because you cannot prove There are no hard artifacts to prove that this is the place of Lord Ra.
GOVINDA Das: If you refer to the scripture, you cannot prove the…
GOVINDA Das: the… the direct protection perman of the scriptures. So what happens then? Then I need to believe. A Mary Shaddahai, it is my faith.
GOVINDA Das: The judge gave the judgment based upon Temple existed before the mosque.
GOVINDA Das: Not because it was a birth pledge, because according to the Bhagavatam.
GOVINDA Das: When Lord Ramachandra went back to the spiritual world, the entire Ayutthhya went into the waters.
GOVINDA Das: Just like Dwarka went into the waters.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, a shraddha is what I believe.
GOVINDA Das: For me, my God, Krishna, Lord Ram, Lord Shiva exists.
GOVINDA Das: And I experienced them.
GOVINDA Das: And somebody says, I don't believe. So, therefore, we cannot argue in regards to changing somebody else's belief. Based upon experience. We can change their belief based upon some superior logic.
GOVINDA Das: At least at that stage of time. I've got a superior logic, I can defeat, but somebody comes with a superior logic, they can defeat my belief. Therefore, shraddha does not require logic.
GOVINDA Das: Shraddha requires personal conviction. It is subjective.
GOVINDA Das: It exists only if we believe.
GOVINDA Das: And what is Dharma?
GOVINDA Das: I'm supposed to do 3-day seminar on Dharma, the whole subject of Dharma.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Dharma is neutral.
GOVINDA Das: Dharma does not take side.
GOVINDA Das: The Battle of Kurukshetra was based upon Dharma, not based upon Sharadhdha.
GOVINDA Das: Bhishmadev was a great devotee of Krishna, but he was fighting on the side of the Kurus.
GOVINDA Das: Right? And because he was fighting on the side of the Kurus, even though he was a devotee of Krishna, still he had to be punished by the Pandavas.
GOVINDA Das: So he was faithful, but not necessarily taking the side of Dharma.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, dharma is an inherent order. It's a functional law.
GOVINDA Das: It operates regardless, it does not based upon belief.
GOVINDA Das: I cannot say I don't believe that fire burns. No, it doesn't matter. It will.
GOVINDA Das: You can't say, I don't believe that water quenches my thirst. No, it does.
GOVINDA Das: And therefore, in Sanat and Dharma, when you say, oh, how can somebody die?
GOVINDA Das: How can they die like this?
GOVINDA Das: Death is inevitable, that is part of Dharmic idea.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, asking question how this can happen to them, how can they die like that, that is part of life.
GOVINDA Das: Natural is that one lives for 100 years, but there is another naturality of death is it can come anytime.
GOVINDA Das: That is how the depth is defined. So, therefore, it is inherent order of functional law. It does not matter whether you believe or not.
GOVINDA Das: And Satya… As it is a reality, there are things, Dharma, ruthu, and Satya.
GOVINDA Das: Dharma is the functional reality, that means I function based upon truth.
GOVINDA Das: Truth is the invisible reality.
GOVINDA Das: And Rutu is a visible reality. Like, we see, seasons are there. There is Grishma Rutu, Sharad Rutu, there is Varsha Rutu, they're visible.
GOVINDA Das: they're observed.
GOVINDA Das: And beyond their observation, there are subtle laws. Subtle laws are satya.
GOVINDA Das: laws which are visible, that is, Ruthu, and submitting to these two is called as Dharva.
GOVINDA Das: Very simply, we are trying to explain. So therefore, when we practice Dharma, Rituals are based upon Dharma.
GOVINDA Das: sometimes those rituals can go beyond Dharma, based upon willip. Like, somebody told a story.
GOVINDA Das: you know, somewhere in Haridwar, people would come from different parts of India.
GOVINDA Das: to perform the Shradda ceremony for their ancestors.
GOVINDA Das: One man came there, he saw there was a huge crowd.
GOVINDA Das: He took the bath, He collected the water.
GOVINDA Das: He offered it to the… the Surya there.
GOVINDA Das: Then again, you had to go to the water, offer from the inside.
GOVINDA Das: Now, he didn't know where to keep his… his, pot.
GOVINDA Das: What it did was… He put the pod upside down.
GOVINDA Das: And put some sand on it, on the top of the pot.
GOVINDA Das: And he went inside the water. And what happened? People saw that.
GOVINDA Das: And eventually, hundreds of pots were lying there.
GOVINDA Das: You know, in the same fashion. Pot was put upside down, and some sand was placed on it.
GOVINDA Das: Unfortunately, many such belief systems have formed based upon hearsay, based upon blind understanding, and sometimes we try to make that as the
GOVINDA Das: Tradition.
GOVINDA Das: There are many traditions which are blindly practiced.
GOVINDA Das: They need to be questioned.
GOVINDA Das: they need to be put to the test, alright? Because…
GOVINDA Das: They sound ritual, but they're against Dharma. Therefore, shraddha is based upon Dharma. When this indict knowledge, when practices Dharma, Satya, and Trutha.
GOVINDA Das: Then, most of our study of psychology
GOVINDA Das: becomes easy when it is integrated with Dharma, Saty, and Drutta, and helps amazingly for our clients.
GOVINDA Das: Yes. So therefore, this is the verse in the Bhagavatam 3rd Kanto.
GOVINDA Das: Nature and its character remains the same.
GOVINDA Das: This cosmic manifestation is as it is now. It was the same in the past, and it will continue in the same in the future. Sometimes people say, because it is Kaliuga, this is… this is what… how it is.
GOVINDA Das: But if you study the Upanishad, if you study the Puranas also, whether it is Kali, whether it is Threata, whether it is Dhapur, whether it is Saty Yuga, duality was always existing. Hiranne Kashipu was there in Saty Yuga.
GOVINDA Das: Ravan was there in Traitha Yuga.
GOVINDA Das: Duryodhan was there in Dwapar Yuga.
GOVINDA Das: And in Kaliuga, the psychological duryodhans are there, the psychological Ravans are there, the psychological kamsas are there, alright? So the yoga do not change the laws of life.
GOVINDA Das: In Sakti Yuga, maybe people did not drink water when they would travel in a water bottle like this.
GOVINDA Das: Alright?
GOVINDA Das: They did not have this kind of water bottle.
GOVINDA Das: But the concept of drinking was there. Simple example, Bhima.
GOVINDA Das: When he was going with his family.
GOVINDA Das: When Mother Kunti wanted to drink water, he had no pots. There was no running water. What does he do? He takes his utarya, the upper cloth, gets into the river.
GOVINDA Das: cleans the cloth. There was a flowing water, and it dips his cloth inside the water and comes running up and squeezes in the mouth of the mother.
GOVINDA Das: the application changed.
GOVINDA Das: The principle did not change.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, never, ever give greater emphasis to being, oh, satta Yuga's very good, and kaluyuga bad. No, every yuga has the duality, and that is what this verse is saying.
Dr. Karan Mittal: True.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So if I… if I discuss, or if I look at it from a toolkit perspective as budding counselors, this session gave us two toolkits, like, two things in the toolkit. The first was
Dr. Karan Mittal: whether we bring in faith, spiritual practices, religion, in as a domain in our therapy with a particular client, and it kind of gave us the Jung's perspective that, what are the parameters that will tell you whether the client is using the spiritual belief?
Dr. Karan Mittal: as a performance, or as probably a bypass. So, if a client comes to you, or a counselor comes to you, that's one parameter. The second thing that we saw today in that toolkit was how beliefs
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, how do we start working with beliefs? So if a person has, like today we saw in one of the breakout rooms, beliefs about spiritual practices, and he's being harsh on himself about
Dr. Karan Mittal: those spiritual practices leading to stress, anxiety, you know, hampering the relationships. So how we dilute those beliefs, how we ask them questions. Of course, it was the first step
Dr. Karan Mittal: Into… into the Sophetic questioning about the beliefs. So we do that, we try to… we don't contradict the beliefs. We don't… we don't directly contradict the beliefs. We…
Dr. Karan Mittal: help them reflect, we help them go deeper, we help them find a source to the belief, and then eventually we give them enough time to reflect and see whether this belief is being functional. Like, most of the people I worked with in the breakout rooms, they had a good part to the belief that it helped them
Dr. Karan Mittal: become what they are today, but it also…
Dr. Karan Mittal: had another dimension that… about stress, about hampering relationships. So we let them, kind of contemplate, and of course, how to work deeper with the beliefs will come later. And now the third part in today's,
Dr. Karan Mittal: toolkit is working with the anthra and Chaturstein. So, antacurant Chattushte, of course, is a Vedantic concept, has been there in our Upanishad Chetzata term, which
Dr. Karan Mittal: kind of splits the mind, or kind of divides the mind based on four different functions. Now, this is not a physical divide, it's a division of functions. And the four… four, probably, the, four components of Antakar and Kharamana
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, Buddhi, and you have heard these names, but how to use it in therapy? We'll just come to that. Ahankara and Chitta. So now, Mana, as we know.
Dr. Karan Mittal: is…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, man is basically that receives, and then kind of reflects and desires. So now, a client or a counselor, when he or she comes to you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: has issues with mana, means there are too many thoughts, too many yeses and nos running in his mind, too many decisions that take too much of his time. The man is kind of having too much of data to process.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So now, you advising this client to chant, to meditate, to do, you know, to focus on the breathing, that's called as breathing awareness. It will help the client because it will reduce the amount of data that is going into the mind.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But…
Dr. Karan Mittal: That same exercise that is helping a person with having issues with mana will not help a person that is having issues with kudi. So Buddhi is basic nishty Atmika, so it helps you make decisions. So that's the… probably the brain part, or the frontal brain part, if I come from a neurological perspective, that helps
Dr. Karan Mittal: whatever decisions are going on, or whatever pending decisions are going on in the mind, the Buddhi helps make the person a decision. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, a person might come to you with…
Dr. Karan Mittal: with having difficulties in making decisions. So then, the same chanting, same meditation, same spiritual practices will not help a person with Buddhi issues, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I had this client of mine who had lots of altruistic behavior, like philanthropic behavior, and couldn't say no to a person. Now, what he was doing was a noble thing. Can I, on the ground of principles, can I teach him, no, you cannot do this, you have to start becoming selfish, or
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or is it a wrong thing that he's doing? No, I cannot do that on the basis of ethics, on the basis of philosophy, etc, we cannot. But it was taking a toll on him, it was putting stress on him. So now you have to equip his Buddhi with certain, probably, tools and techniques to make decisions in different, different aspects of his life. So, the instrument that I used was, I told the client.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That…
Dr. Karan Mittal: If you want to do something for a particular person, unless the person is, like, into a particular group, which we kind of segregated earlier, parents and, you know, the closest people, I asked them if the situation was reversed, if you needed the same help.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Will the opposite person come and help you in the same way, the way you are going out of the way to the person? So it gave him a break.
Dr. Karan Mittal: it gave him a buffer system. I'm not saying that he used to… he has to use this same law in every relationship, but he… it gave him a break or a buffer to use this law or a rule in relationships that are very distant to him, or not in his circle of, you know, proximity or relationship, etc. So, when the client comes to you with a Buddhi struggle.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You cannot tell him to focus on breath, chant, meditate. You have to equip him with Buddhi-based things. It could be journaling, it could be learning a few techniques, it could be discipline, it could be things that will help him make those decisions faster.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Is I-ness. It's basically how you associate with different things in your life. So, the Ahankara is one of the most
Dr. Karan Mittal: flexible thing that we find in Indian philosophy, it can be with the body, just like, I feel only my body is mine. So whatever measures I take in my life will be for taking care of my body.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But if I have that ahankara or association with my family members also, so my… the width or the expanse of my ahankara is now wider.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I take care of my family members, I go out with… I go out and try to help them, and in Hindu philosophy or Indian philosophy, it expands all the way across to the Earth, and also the universe. So how much you associate yourself, how much highness is there with different, different
Dr. Karan Mittal: Issues, and different, different people, and different, different situations in your life will make you act accordingly, will cause issues accordingly, and the treatment also has to differ.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? We'll come to each one of these in detail. And the fourth is Chitta, which is your storehouse of
Dr. Karan Mittal: memories and impressions and sanskars and vasnas, what we talk about. So, like, yesterday we were seeing John Locke. John Locke said that every person is born like a blank slate, tabular sign. He or she can be conditioned.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But Indian philosophy integrates that there are certain vasnas, sanskaras, that run across lifetimes, and also in a particular life, if you have experienced a childhood which was in a particular way, those vasanas and sanskaras will run across.
Dr. Karan Mittal: in the future decades of your life. So, when a person comes to me with
Dr. Karan Mittal: Undiagnosed or with unexplainable fears, anxieties, unexplainable thoughts and emotions. The man Buddhi Hangara can give you symptomatic treatment, but then you'll have to go to the Chittra and try to tap into the different
Dr. Karan Mittal: memories that exist. So, suppose
Dr. Karan Mittal: So I had this person who kind of had issues with confidence, like, you know, graduated from IIT, did MBA from one of the IMUs, couldn't ask
Dr. Karan Mittal: the right salary, or couldn't quote the right salary for himself, whenever he applied for a job. Now, that confidence was not there in his or her particular ability. Now, there was no explainable reason. The man knows that my worth is this much.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The Buddhi also knows that my worth is this much. The Ankara says that I want that much, but he's not able to quote.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So how would you explain this? So then, when we started digging in, digging in, digging in, there was a time in the child… childhood, of course, and I'm just…
Dr. Karan Mittal: mentioning gist of the issue and the diagnosis, but of course, it went across seven, eight sessions. So when we went into childhood, there was a time when he went up to the stage, and, you know, there was so much that people started laughing, he urinated in his pants. He lost the confidence and ability
Dr. Karan Mittal: To kind of go on the stage and speak for himself that particular day.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Whatever he did in ITIM was his goodby working, his intelligence working, but that ability to ask or speak what's right for himself, or what he wants to speak, he was… it got lost to her in that way.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So working on that memory kind of helped us, you know, work on that entanglement with that issue, and then
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course, that issue got resolved. So, you have to understand where is the issue. A person coming to you is coming for a relationship issue. Now, someone asked in the chat that… that how do… I gave… I gave that example of that female who expected the husband to
Dr. Karan Mittal: follow the, you know, follow that particular spiritual tradition. So how do you understand, how would you kind of segregate
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… So, the thing I asked that female was that
Dr. Karan Mittal: Is the marriage all about the husband kind of following that particular spiritual tradition that you follow?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Is the couple relationship all about he following it or not following it?
Dr. Karan Mittal: And that gave her that insight, that the marriage is not just about me telling, you know, that husband following that particular tradition. It's much more which I kind of, you know, forgot about, that it's we, it's our family, it's we too, and it's not just about this spiritual tradition. So, kind of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: inquiring?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So here, what was happening over here is… why I took this example here is the ahangar of the female, the highness of the female was…
Dr. Karan Mittal: focused on that particular spiritual tradition. The Hankara of the female was focused on her husband, and now she was trying to push this ahangara of the spiritual tradition on the husband, causing the issue between husband and the female.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So I had to detach her association of that spiritual tradition as a definition of the relationship between the husband and the girl.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So when you understand that the Hangara of this spiritual tradition is right, and my husband also should follow it, and what will the other people in the spiritual tradition say if my husband, after 20 years, is also not able to follow this? All these things had to be detangled. So the Hangara had to be retrieved back
Dr. Karan Mittal: from the spiritual tradition, and the spiritual tradition hampering the relationship. So you start analyzing that which of those… these four functionalities are basically affecting that plant.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And accordingly, the maneuvers, or the modalities that you use will change. One, like Prabhuji, I think, said yesterday also, one solution for everything doesn't
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so same chanting meditation won't work for a person having good issues. Same journaling, writing, observing your thoughts will not work for a person having chitty shoes. So you have to kind of play, or you have to kind of have a few techniques in your bag, and then use it as for the functionalities of the mind.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Soup?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So I think this part, probably should be to take it tomorrow and take up questions right now, because Anthrakaran itself is a huge part.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, before I get into this detail, I want you to kind of map your own antagon. Take 5 minutes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And… Before we get into the details of Antakr and Chattusha.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I want you to kind of… Take these folk.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Questions?
Dr. Karan Mittal: And it would also serve as a reflection for you. Maybe you can take a screenshot and all that also.
GOVINDA Das: I didn't realize that I was mute.
GOVINDA Das: So I'm speaking on my own.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So…
GOVINDA Das: So the… the… the four, Mana, Buddhi, Ahankar, and Chitta.
GOVINDA Das: That these four things, again, this is the foundational idea.
GOVINDA Das: For practicing counselors, whether spiritual or professional, that…
GOVINDA Das: You cannot define where do they reside.
GOVINDA Das: You cannot define Exactly, you can only define their function.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, if you want to study more about Manbutti, Hankar Sankhya gives in great detail the Bhagavatam Third Kant also.
GOVINDA Das: 26th chapter of 3rd Canto.
GOVINDA Das: Gives in great detail.
GOVINDA Das: Now, Man Buddhi ahankar, how do we know?
GOVINDA Das: Hungarmint?
GOVINDA Das: Where you experience hurt of Urugu, alright? How can they speak this to me? That is a Hankar.
GOVINDA Das: The feeling in that statement, that is mine.
GOVINDA Das: And how is basically questioning.
GOVINDA Das: So it is explained, the Bhagavatam explains, one can understand what is mind, what is Buddhi, what is Ahankar, based upon their function.
GOVINDA Das: Not based upon their position.
GOVINDA Das: Failing his mind?
GOVINDA Das: Questioning is Bhutti.
GOVINDA Das: And feeling hurt is ego.
GOVINDA Das: I am Indian, that is ego.
GOVINDA Das: You know what? They offended me.
GOVINDA Das: You know, ego is there, and the mind is also there, and now you'll teach them the lesson. That is Bhutti.
GOVINDA Das: And what does it do? All these impressions…
GOVINDA Das: They go back and store themselves in Chitta.
GOVINDA Das: And what is chitta? Chitta, according to modern science, is called as cognitive bias.
GOVINDA Das: Which is samskara, and in our next session, we will certainly take that. The cognitive bias, one of the greatest tragedy for a spiritual counselor or a professional counselor, having a bias, a gender bias, cultural bias.
GOVINDA Das: There are many biases, and these are all collective biases, it's called as samskara, which is stored in the Chitra.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, of course, we'll deal with the Anthakaran Chattushte next time again, and I'll also add more tools of how to work with each of these faculties, whether it's Manabuddhi, Ankara, Chikta. But for now, I just want you to take 5 minutes, or 2-3 minutes, and probably contemplate on these questions, and maybe we can do a deeper contemplation
Dr. Karan Mittal: Over the next week.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Because…
Dr. Karan Mittal: The toolkits we will now use in the third session would be based on these different, different faculties that I'm the current Chatush therapists.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then we can probably take questions for today, and… yes, brochure.
GOVINDA Das: Yep.
GOVINDA Das: Question answered that?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, question answers, and in the meantime, they can also reflect on the four questions, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Maybe you can raise your hands and maybe type it in the chat, and we can take question and answers for today.
jithendra myla: Hare Krishna Ruji.
jithendra myla: So about Dharma, It is,
jithendra myla: very vast topic, sometimes I get lost.
jithendra myla: To understand it.
jithendra myla: And also, when it comes to the Gauri Vaishna movement.
jithendra myla: Is it Dharma to follow the Krishna conscious path, or is it… Is it not, like…
jithendra myla: there is, in any of Prabhupada books, there is not much mention of, Dharma. It's all about Krishna consciousness.
jithendra myla: And also, when it comes to Desh Bhakti.
jithendra myla: There is no mention, like, the devotees has to be loyal to their country, or…
jithendra myla: Anything related to that, and that is also puzzles me.
jithendra myla: If you can elaborate on that.
GOVINDA Das: So you asked that question, very dharma changes, does it dharma… that is also your question in law of the universe. Some people.
jithendra myla: Yeah.
GOVINDA Das: changes based time, place, and circumstances. Application will change.
GOVINDA Das: But the principle will never change. I give the example of water drinking, right? Drinking of water is the principle. How do you drink? That is an application.
GOVINDA Das: Now, when you speak about your own spiritual practice.
GOVINDA Das: there is 3 Dharmas. There is a Swabhava Dharma, there is Swarupa Dharma, and there is Apod Dharma.
GOVINDA Das: In the first Kent of the Bhagavatam, in the teachings of Vishma Dev, some indication is given, but if you go deeper, if you go into elaborate, the Mahabharata explains. What is Saurupa Dharma? Saurupa Dharma is your constitutional nature.
GOVINDA Das: Jiva's constitutional nature, For a Vaishnava, it could be service.
GOVINDA Das: It could be, you know, lovingly serving God. That is your Swuru Pudara.
GOVINDA Das: You know, that is uncompromising.
GOVINDA Das: But at the same time, there is Swabhava Dharma, or Swadharma. What is Svadharma? Swadhdharma is basically your mental…
GOVINDA Das: Intellectual Man Buddhi ahankar, the three. Man Buddhi Ahankar designs your Varana.
GOVINDA Das: your disposition.
GOVINDA Das: If you're a warrior.
GOVINDA Das: Right, even if you try, warrior is not that you only fight. Warrior is basically protection, fighting for justice, taking administrative role, right? If somebody forces you
GOVINDA Das: To become a garland maker all the time, you can do it for 1 day, you can do it for 2 days, you can do it for 1 year.
GOVINDA Das: As Krishna explains in the Bhagavad Gita, that because it is not according to your nature, nigram, when you artificially try to hold, at some point of time, it causes a rebellion.
GOVINDA Das: Because with this body, we are not always operating on the platform of sorupadharma, our constitutional nature, our conditional nature. Therefore, Pravada explains
GOVINDA Das: If you study his books, one has to doubt tell his propensity.
GOVINDA Das: In the 12th chapter, right?
GOVINDA Das: when Krishna brought back all the Yadavas, in the 10th Kent of the Bhagavadim, there is a description.
GOVINDA Das: Only when the Yadavas came back to their original place.
GOVINDA Das: I'll send that quote in the group.
GOVINDA Das: In the 5th khant of the Vhagavatam, there is a large description, what is Bharat?
GOVINDA Das: You know, what does constitute a Bharat? Why Devutas want to take birth? Lord Chaitanya said Bharata Bhubile. Deisha Bhakti is not a separate identity.
GOVINDA Das: Alright, if you're a warrior, right, you have to fight for a country. There are so many soldiers who are practicing spirituality, but they're also taking a different administrative position.
GOVINDA Das: You know, you're taking responsibility for your family, right? They're not contradiction to our sorupadharma.
GOVINDA Das: And what is Apat Dharma? Apart Dharma is a Dharma when there is a circumstantial situation and the Pandavas had to become cook.
GOVINDA Das: Arjuna had become a dancer.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Because subsistence
GOVINDA Das: Rotikapada Makan, like, you have to sustain your body. You may be an engineer, you may be a doctor, but in emergency, you may have to clean pots, you may have to drive the truck. That is a circumstantial duty, like the Pandavas did. So, the Shastras explain very clearly there is a Saurupudharma.
GOVINDA Das: there is, Swadharma, and there is Apat Dharma, and they're integrated, they are not separate from each other.
jithendra myla: Okay.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah.
jithendra myla: You can do it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Ruiz, there's a question. I've observed a lot of people very strong in their sadhana, but due to a hankar, or due to strong belief, they tend to forget humility.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How to understand such a person? Is the person right? How to make person understand that they are close to financialism?
GOVINDA Das: That's what we… we discussed this. This is the… this is the danger of practicing spirituality.
GOVINDA Das: It's not the spirituality itself is the problem, it is the person who's practicing spirituality.
GOVINDA Das: If they feel there is a story told by one very great saint, Pajar Swami.
GOVINDA Das: You know, he recently passed away, extremely…
GOVINDA Das: great soul. He said, one time.
GOVINDA Das: How Brahman was doing his Gayatri without fail, never missed his Gayatri.
GOVINDA Das: And one day, he got up late.
GOVINDA Das: He could not get up only.
GOVINDA Das: And Kali personified, Kali, Kali personified, woke him up. Ari, come on, get up, get up! You have to perform your Gayatri.
GOVINDA Das: And this Brahmana got up immediately and took fast bath, and he performed his Gayatra, he felt satisfied. And then he was shocked, how is that Kali woke me up?
GOVINDA Das: Then he asked the Kali, why, why you woke me up? He said, because you'll have the pride of never missing your Gayatri.
GOVINDA Das: Alright?
GOVINDA Das: Sometime the purity itself becomes a contamination. I'm so pure, others are very impure.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, yes, That strong sadhana
GOVINDA Das: Has the power to give rise to ahankar instead of confidence.
GOVINDA Das: When confidence and ankh are.
GOVINDA Das: are working very close to each other, rather than Atma Vishwas, it can lead to ahankar, and Ahankar, what does it do? It basically makes one feel inferior to others.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, when Krishna, Lord Ram, beautiful story of Lord Ram, when he was riding with Mathali, the Indrush chariot driver.
GOVINDA Das: While the Battle of Ram Raman was going on.
GOVINDA Das: And then Lord Ram realized, actually, he's not my chariot driver, he's Indra's chariot driver.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, he said, sorry, I was pushing you.
GOVINDA Das: So, Ram was humble enough to say, so therefore, yes, Sadhana… is very important.
GOVINDA Das: But the flip side of that sadhana is that one can become arrogant.
GOVINDA Das: Overconfident, and undermine others' position, and becomes spiritually fanatic.
Dr. Karan Mittal: To Ramji, you can ask the question.
GOVINDA Das: Vikram has a question. Can you explain Chitta's subconscious mind?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Pujay replied. So, yeah, Chitta is very similar to subconscious mind. Of course, in Indian perspective, subconscious mind also has past life sanctaras and vasanas, etc, as well, but in Freud, they kind of go a bit superficial. It's all about this life, and then they… in regression therapy.
Dr. Karan Mittal: We also kind of,
Dr. Karan Mittal: postulate an unconscious mind, which has the past life sanskaras and it, okay? So, unconscious plus subconscious becomes the chit of IKS.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, Shibamjde?
shubham singh: Jay, namaste. I have two questions. First one is that, when we are reading about Ntakaran Chetusta.
shubham singh: So can we do a categorization of all these four on the basis of 3 good?
shubham singh: First one, and second one is that if, this one is to Dr. Karan. If, as a counselor.
shubham singh: We are facing some client who is having a car issue.
shubham singh: And because of that Ankar, he's not able to… Gel with the colleagues…
shubham singh: Because of his tendency of claiming that he's the doer of everything.
shubham singh: So, can we deal that person with the perspective of Nishkam, how Anasabh tendency, just to nudge that personality into that direction?
shubham singh: to perform Nishkam Bhav with unattached tendencies.
shubham singh: To come… to bring him out of this tendency.
shubham singh: Or is there any other way we can do? What is your perspective on this?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Provoji, would you like to take the first question first?
GOVINDA Das: You take, you take both, then I'll add.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, so I think the last question…
Dr. Karan Mittal: If a person thinks about the doership and the ego, etc, you trying to kind of condition him into this nishkam thing also will become a source of his ego.
Dr. Karan Mittal: that I do things, and I'm not attached to the fall of things. So, these are sensitive things. The one thing what we do is, we try to find the source of that tahankar, or that doership.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That is the person trying to fill in the… fill in a vacuum.
Dr. Karan Mittal: by getting egoistic or, you know, claiming leadership and is not able… not… and that's why he's not able to gel with colleagues. So we try to see that, is there any vacuum that he's artificially trying to fill in with this ego and this sense of worship? That is the right approach to kind of dealing with this case. Sometimes what happens is if a person is egoistic, and then you
Dr. Karan Mittal: impose this philosophy of Nishkam, karma, etc. He follows it mechanistically, and this also becomes an added flaw to his ego, that I do things with Nishkam, however, and others do it with, you know, expecting, etc. So it's a very sensitive thing, you have to see.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Where is the vacuum, and which vacuum the client is trying to fill in by claiming this ego. And your Anthataran Chatushta, yes, it can be seen from anything in the world. If you go from the Sankhya philosophy, the world is made from figures.
GOVINDA Das: Karanji, just to add back to that, you know, we will come to that community bias.
GOVINDA Das: In a very thing that, as a client, if it's your… you know, if you're… if you're… if you're a manager, you might see it as an ankar. But if you're a counselor, you will see it as a disease.
GOVINDA Das: Rather than identifying it as a Hankara, you may identify it is not a healthy behavior. Why is he ahankari?
GOVINDA Das: That is the route we have to find out.
GOVINDA Das: You know, because again, administration, like… like, I remember talking to one very highly elevated scholar. He said a police has to see crime everywhere.
GOVINDA Das: Potential criminal he has to see everywhere.
GOVINDA Das: A social reformer has to see, potentially, Contributing people everywhere.
GOVINDA Das: And a psychologist has to see everyone as a person can be cured.
GOVINDA Das: they cannot judge. Therefore, you know, we have to define whether I'm an administrative head or am I a counselor. If I'm a counselor, I cannot see it as an ankhar. I have to see it as some issue, I need to deal with it.
GOVINDA Das: If he's a… if you're an administrative head, and that is causing conflict amongst many people, then either you create a discipline for his behavior, or if it is not working, then he has to be sent to a professional person to deal with it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And regarding a second question about seeing the…
Dr. Karan Mittal: the anti-current Chatushte from Sri Guna perspective, anything in the world, as per Sanki philosophy, the whole universe is Sri Gunat Mika, that it gets created from Thrigunas. So, yes, it can be seen.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Probably beyond the scope of this training, but maybe I'll mention which of this, you know, falls under which Ebola. So that can be just taken and mentioned in the next slide… in the next session.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. Suraji? Roshi, would you like to add something? No.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, basically, the Sankhya philosophy, including in the Bhagavatam, it explains that, you know, the mind itself comes from Rajogunha.
GOVINDA Das: And, sorry, mine comes from Sattvogoda.
GOVINDA Das: And then in the beginning of this Rishti, and then Buddhi comes from Rajogodha.
GOVINDA Das: And within that also, like, some we will touch based upon, three modes of material chill, three guna. Again, another fascinating concept for Indian knowledge system, helping people in integrated psychology.
GOVINDA Das: Everything has to be properly analyzed through three modes of material nature, or three gunas. Yes, very much.
Dr. Karan Mittal: energy?
GOVINDA Das: Yep.
suraj racha: Cheers.
suraj racha: So, I'd like to ask a question, which I don't know is in the scope of today's session or not, but these tools which you have explained is really, really useful, but
suraj racha: And the intention which I'm… which I am putting this person is, as a counselor, we have to create the most impact to the mentor. For example, if someone comes to me for counseling and starts with a problem, now they are suffering, and they are also seeking for a solution, but most of the time.
suraj racha: the mental framework in which they are at the moment, they're not ready to complicate things further. They're just like, just give me something simple to deal with. Do not, like, break things further, or do not make things more complex. There is one line of solution, if you would like to give me, then I'll accept. Otherwise, these things are not being digested by me.
suraj racha: So, how do you deal with such a situation?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sure, it's a big one.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, current expert, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, so, I think, Surahji, so, I think,
Dr. Karan Mittal: Right now, we are in… we are on the day two, and we are just adding a few tools to our kitty. It's like, we in therapy call it the kitty, or it's our bag. So we are just trying to do more of self-work right now, and also taking in a few tools that will help fly.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, the client… the kind of client that you are talking about just wants a solution. It's like you are having fever and just give a parasitomone, doesn't want to get into, the causes and diagnosis and treatment, etc. So that… those tools are also available, but that's, I think.
Dr. Karan Mittal: even… even to get to that tool, you'll have to understand the psyche of the client, of how… what tool will work. So, in psychology, there are tools which go to the subconscious, conscious behavioral tools, and then, you know, there are… there are just going into the chittas, that is regression, hypnosis, etc. So, there are different kind of tools, and right now, the behavioral tool that you are asking for, I think.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's probably not meant, for…
Dr. Karan Mittal: the first few sessions, it's like getting, just giving that paracetamol. It will take some more time for us to develop the understanding.
Dr. Karan Mittal: To reach a prescription of that tool, yeah. I think I've… yeah, that's how I can frame it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If so.
GOVINDA Das: Actually, they can be offered simple. Ayurved will provide a food solution also. By simply changing the habits in their food also, their problem can be solved, but because they come with such a complexity and want a simple solution, that itself shows that their problem is very complex.
GOVINDA Das: You know, they may not… they may not take this simple solution very easily.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah.
GOVINDA Das: We'll stop here, right? And we will come back on next week.
GOVINDA Das: Saturday, and we will commence with our, the chitta, elaborating in regards to cognitive bias. Very important, because this is what creates a judgment.
GOVINDA Das: For a counselor.
GOVINDA Das: Alright?
GOVINDA Das: And with that, cognitive bias, when we understand, it's a very fascinating subject. And along with that, we will discuss integrated approach to
GOVINDA Das: Dealing with the patient, or the client, or the spiritual spirit.
GOVINDA Das: Thank you for your kindness.
Renuka Bhuta: We'll be getting some material to understand, because when you're talking on that level, it is very difficult to understand.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, we will share the thoughts.
Renuka Bhuta: like me.
GOVINDA Das: We will share the notes. And if you have any questions, we have a group. You can, you know, throughout the week, we can take few questions also.
GOVINDA Das: Not an issue. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: In a day or two, I'll send the toolkits of whatever we acquired in the first two days, like, you know, the faith-based counseling, the chitta-based, and also the belief. So maybe by Tuesday, I'll get those materials for you to read and follow.
GOVINDA Das: No. Yeah. Thank you.
Renuka Bhuta: Thank you.
Rutuja Nayak: Thank you.
Renuka Bhuta: Okay, sure.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Thank you, namaste.